Records of the Locomobile Company of America Blueprints
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
Records of the Locomobile Company of America Blueprints
1924-1926
Locomobile Company of America
BHC-MSS 005
.5 linear feet 1 manuscript box
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
Following the purchase of the Bridgeport based Locomobile Company of America by Durant Motors in 1922, Locomobile continued to produce autos and automotive parts. The blueprints within this collection document what was produced from 1924 to 1926.
Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Biography
The Locomobile Company of America began its life in Watertown, Massachusetts in 1899. Founded by John Walker and Amzi Lorenzo Barber, the two began the company when they witnessed the steam powered car that was built by Francis and Freelan Stanley. Walker and Barber acquired the plans, and originally called their company The Automobile Company of America. That name was already taken, and Barber is given the credit for changing the name to the Locomobile Company of America. They quickly involved others with the venture, including the company's first president Samuel Todd Davis Jr. who filled that position until his death in 1915.
The company moved to Bridgeport, Connecticut, in 1900, and initially produced steam cars. During this time, steam, electric, and gasoline cars were all being developed, with no one particular type leading the pack. Around 1901, gasoline cars began to gain traction, and the Locomobile Company of America brought in engineer Andrew L. Riker to assist in developing their cars further. Prior to being hired by Locomobile, Riker had owned the Riker Motor Vehicle Company, based out of Elizabeth, New Jersey, which produced electric cars. In 1903, the company began producing gasoline powered cars exclusively.
As the car developed, so did the brand, and Locomobile eschewed an assembly line focus for one that emphasized the handcrafted nature of each automobile. This developed into a boast that no more than four Locomobiles were produced each day, making Locomobile an early luxury brand. With lighting provided by Tiffany and Company's, plush interiors, and careful attention to detail, this boast was used as a marketing and selling point. In addition, the small number of cars produced allowed the Locomobile Company of America to remain in touch with owners, which helped to ensure customer loyalty, as well as excellent service.
The Locomobile Company of America also participated in early automobile races. A key victory was won at the Vanderbilt Cup race on October 24, 1908, when the car now affectionately known as the Old 16 won the race. That victory made Locomobile the only American car company to win the race, as all previous winners had been manufacturers from outside of the United States. In 1911, the Locomobile Company of America started to manufacture commercial trucks. These worm drive trucks had a number of various body models based on the need of the individual, and it also proved useful in the First World War. The demand for the truck, later renamed the Riker Truck in honor of Locomobile engineer Andrew L. Riker, helped grow the Bridgeport economy during World War One.
Locomobile was bought by William C. Durant and incorporated into Durant Motors in 1922. Durant helped to found General Motors. During this time Locomobiles were still produced, but until 1925, only the Model 48 was produced under the Locomobile marquee. 1925 allowed for the introduction of the 8-66 Junior Eight, then several more models after that, but Durant motors went under in 1929. Production lasted until 1933, but after that Locomobile as a brand was no more.
As of today, there are some remaining Locomobiles. The Old 16 racer is owned by the Henry Ford Museum, and some models appear in auction houses from time to time, retailing for extremely high prices.
Scope and Content of Collection
The blueprints relate to various automotive parts produced by the Locomobile Company of America following the purchase of Locomobile by Durant Motors in 1922. Due to the paper, the blueprints are fragile.
Arrangement
Arranged by blueprint number. Various dates on on each blueprint, relating to the production process.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Locomobile Company of America
- Inventory
  - 200023, front spring bumper, February 25, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 200072, Clutch control shaft bracket assembly, December 14, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 200081, Spark plug gasket, November 17, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 201214, Torque arm, September 1, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 201388, Transmission counter shaft, April 12, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 201396, Rear wheel hub, June 22, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 201398, Cylinder head stud nut, October 3, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 201399, Rear axel shaft key, July 2, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 201408, rear cross member, January 1, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 201473, Gasoline strainer body, August 11, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 201474, Gasoline strainer bottom, August 11, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 201475. Gasoline strainer top, August 11, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 201477, Gasoline tank filler, January 15, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 201478, Gasoline tank filler flange, August 11, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 201487, Gasoline gauge washer, March 8, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 201501, Torque arm insulator, September 14, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 201510, Wheel ring disteel, June 14, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 201511, Shock absorber strap anchor, May 5, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 201514, Oil fitting straight, March 14, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 201515, Oil fitting, July 8, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 201517, Radiator filler neck sleeve, June 15, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 201519, Radiator [?], June 29, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 201522, Clutch under pan, August 31, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 201524, Radiator cap washer, March 26, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 201527, Tire pump hose, July 22, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 201529, Head lamp bracket, December 6, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 201530, Head lamp bracket, October 2, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 201532, Head lamp bracket, brace end, October 24, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 201533, Head lamp bracket, brace tube, December 6, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 201540 and 201541, Running board, November 25, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 201545, Clutch brake shoe stud, March 18, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 201547, Transmission case cover plate plunger, March 15, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 201548, Tire pan assembly, March 17, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - 201550, Tire pan assembly complete, April 13, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - 201551, Tire pan, March 13, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - 201556, Stop lamp switch, September 4, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - 201562, Hood catch plate, March 14, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - 201569, Tire strap (upper) pin, March 18, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - 201582, Tire strap (lower) pin, March 18, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - 201585, Tire carrier shoe support extension, March 25, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - 201644, Hood handle, April 14, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - 202046, Rear axle shaft nut, June 16, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - 202472, Accelerator pedal hinge pin, July 20, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - 203476 and 203477, Radiator splash apron backer, March 10, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - 202560, Wiring harness, October 25, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - 203474, Tire carrier tie bar assembly - two tires, March 4, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - 203516, Muffler pipe (lower) assembly - heater type, April 16, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - 203517, Muffler pipe (lower) assembly - heater type, April 16, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - 250144 and 250145, Rear quarters rear leather trim, July 1, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Parts list for model 48 19000 series, April 7, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 50)